first we will discuss active power the
active power can be computed as 1/ half
of the total capacitance of the circuit
where the capacitance can be seen as
roughly proportional to chip area so
larger chips will have more of this the
next factor is voltage Square this is
the power supply voltage the higher the
power supply voltage the higher the
power is and this relationship is
quadratic so doubling of the power
supply voltage will actually quadr the
power the next factor is clock frequency
this is the gigahertz number that you
normally see on a processor
specification and finally the alpha is
the activity Factor without this Alpha
we are assuming that the processor is
constantly switching every clock cycle
all of its transistors so Alpha really
says that for example only 10% of the
processor transistors are actually
active in any given clock cycle now
let's see what happens to power if after
after 2 years we reduced the size of the
processor to one half of what it was
because of Technology Improvement the
new capacitance is half of what it was
for One processor however because we
want to build a more powerful processor
we put two of them on the chip so the C
new really is equal to C old let's say
that the voltage and the frequency stay
the same and let's say that it's still
the same processor design so the same
percentage of transistors are active
that means really that the active power
is relatively unchanged if we do this
what we have is effectively a processor
that consumes the same amount of power
but it does have twice the number of
cores that it had before so it's it's
actually twice as capable
computationally because each of those
cores is still operating at the same
frequency as before and it's really a
very similar to the old core in reality
smaller transistors are going to be
faster so we can increase the clock
frequency of the processor tool so let's
say that the new clock frequency is 25%
higher than the old one that increases
the power consumed so it's now twice as
fast because of the number of cores
another 25% Improvement because of this
but the overall power consumption is now
higher smaller transistors however may
let us lower the power supply voltage
while maintaining the same speed so
let's say that the new power supply
voltage is equal to 0.8 of the old power
supply voltage that allows us to have a
significantly lower power consumption
because of this Square relationship so
0.8 squar is
0.64 if we put these two together we can
get something like the voltage we don't
lower it as much because if we did then
we couldn't also increase the frequency
so we lower it only a little bit the
frequency we cannot increase it it as
much because if we did we would have to
keep the same power supply voltage as
before so let's say we only increase the
frequency by a factor of
1.1 if you now apply this equation we
get that the new power is about 90% of
the old Power so what we got is now we
have a chip that is having two cores
instead of one it has a lower power
supply voltage but a higher frequency so
each of these cores is 10% faster than
the one used to be and yet we have lower
power consumption this is why it's so
important for active power to have the
technology Improvement reduce the size
of transistors and we also have to
realize that in order to get power
improvements we really really really
need to lower the voltage